Ellen Fenton Diaries of Travels to Boulogne-sur-Mer
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Diaries
  - Diary, 1860 July 17-August 11; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (134 pages); 11 pages of watercolor drawings; 3 letters; 1 playbill; 1 programme; 2 clippings; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 8)
    This trip to Boulogne is also distinguished by the presence of Mrs. Watson, an elderly charwoman whom Fenton brings along as a second servant. As Fenton's husband does not consent to Mrs. Watson's presence on the trip, nor is the woman cognizant of Fenton's designs for her in Boulogne, the departure from London is described as a "smuggling affair" (1). For fear that Mrs. Watson would escape, Fenton sends her by train to St. Paul's, where the family would pass by coach on the way to London Bridge wharf. Fenton is very amused by Mrs. Watson's first experience of foreign travel, noting how she kept awake for the entire steamship journey, and tried to trick the other servant, Charlotte, into admitting that the steamship was bound for New York. Geraldine and Fenton nickname the elderly woman "Mrs. Lacelles Jerningham-Birmingham" and Fenton admits "crying with laughter" at the woman's unusual queries: "did the vessel move, for it seemed for a long time, just in the same place… did the sea boil, it was like water in a kettle, bubbling and frothing[?]" (5). When at Boulogne, Fenton enjoys taking Mrs. Watson to St. Nicolas to observe her wonderment at Catholic ritual. When the Fenton family visit the dungeons, Mrs. Watson is unnerved by the excursion. At the citadel, the family comes across a company of soldiers from the 83rd regiment "looking as if they were a rank to fire on us" (56). When Mrs. Watson declares she can go no further, Fenton notes that she was "obliged to go with us, when I shewed her, she could not stay 'to be shot at,' which speech evidently went quite home" (57). As they descend into the "dismal chamber of horrors," Mrs. Watson again complains that she cannot go on, and Fenton confesses "I am quite ashamed to own, I felt not one particle of sympathy, but told her, if she went back or stood still, she must get lost, or shut up for life" (57). Fenton is herself unnerved, however, when the family is followed by a gaunt man of whom she includes a sketch and description: "I turned, and closely examined him – such a tremendous face! Long, flat, wrinkled, and with a look half stolid, half animal" (57-58).
    Another victim of Fenton and Geraldine's fun-making is the eccentric and pestering Dr. Adolphus, who is represented in a few of Fenton's drawings in this volume. Fenton describes the family's several attempts of avoiding him, especially at balls. "We flew whenever we saw him," jests Fenton, noting that they "had the fun to see him vainly hunting for us all" (30). She and Geraldine play more than a few pranks on the unsuspecting doctor, inventing a "Miss Perrot" for him to pursue. When the doctor asks if Fenton's young friend, Miss Gattey was this Miss Perrot, Fenton says "yes, for the fun of it, and trusting to the chapter of accidents" (36). When Fanny Emmett, the Gattey family, and a Mr. Whitsed come over for tea, Dr. Adolphus arrives, acting "so absurd, that the idea of making him the general butt, was quite irresistible to us all" (52). The group plays "Mother Crump," a game that involves a chair in the middle of the room that the captain of the game was to sit upon. Fenton sketches the doctor "shaking one finger and one foot, on his uneasy seat, rolling about on what he intended for graceful attitudes." (see page 52-53). This game goes on until two in the morning, when a neighbor threatens to call the police.
    In addition to humorous social foibles, Fenton's journal draws attention to political events that effect the family's experience of Boulogne in 1860. Growing tensions between the English and French are precipitated by Lord Palmerston's speech to parliament, "so remarkable against the entente cordiale" (74). On the 23rd of July, Palmerston announced that England was now threatened by their ally's growing economic and military supremacy, warning that it might have to defend itself against the power. Wondering "if some explosion is at hand," this new distrust registers in the ballrooms of Boulogne, says Fenton, where a French Colonel whom Fenton tries to match with a partner angrily prevents her party from so much as sitting nearby (74).
    The latter part of Fenton's trip is colored by her interaction with a group of Irish prisoners bound for Dublin. A clipping, pasted in her journal (between pages 56-57) explains that 116 Irishmen were led to believe by a Mr. Sullivan, of The Nation, that they would be paid handsomely to join the Pope's army. The article reports that they were sent to Rome on an arduous journey, and once there, made to live in wretched conditions with little food to survive. Fenton speaks to these men, now en route back to Ireland after refusing to sign the work contracts, and finds them "dreadfully exhausted… They had been confined ten days in Cells, down deep in a prison" (92). Fenton takes the opportunity to rail against Catholicism: "I said, I hoped they would give up their false religion, now they had experienced the gross deception it all was, to them, and which Protestants, in vain, warned them of." Yet she also seems pleased by the men's reaction to her perceived Irish roots. Fenton resolves to take food and brandy to the groups of Irish prisoners as they pass through Boulogne.
    Diaries; Watercolors; Travel sketches -- France; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary, 1862 August 25-September 9; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (170 pages); 42 pages of watercolor drawings; 1 card; 3 clippings; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 9)
    Holograph journal describing Ellen Fenton's family vacation at Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1862. Includes 42 pages of watercolor drawings of local people, scenery and landscapes to accompany journal descriptions--the most numerous of all of her volumes. This volume contains three clippings, "The Nouveau Riche in Boulogne" (September 24, 1862), "Our Leader of Last Week" (October 1), a brief synopsis of the burlesque "A Fuss Amongst the Fogies" (October 8), along with letters to the editor. It also includes Mademoiselle Legendre's calling card, affixed above her portrait. Pages 27-32 are partially or completely torn. Pages 91-94 are missing. The journal is incomplete or missing the last few pages.
    Fenton begins this volume describing her "heavy heart," but quickly moves on from her unspecified sorrows by reminding "I intend to write to amuse you, dear Mrs. Ibotson, and my children, who in years to come, may read this, will know it all too well" (1). Fenton's husband is entirely absent from this volume, perhaps an indication of strained relations. Another of her sorrows seems to be the death of her child, Horace, who is recalled by his grief-stricken mother. It appears that Fenton may have anticipated his early death, possibly due to a congenital illness: "Responsible for his birth, for his training, for the life he leads, yet powerless for good. Seeing the Vessel hurrying to a wreck, and yet told, that if I speak, I shall hasten its doom" (20).
    Despite this melancholy, Fenton continues to engage in lighthearted fun-making, and she especially enjoys challenging the snobberies of others. When she observes an artist aboard her steamship who "affected exclusiveness, and after several disgusted inspections of people at breakfast, he waited to breakfast alone," Fenton decides to sit down "opposite to his Lordship, the artist! Did he not stare!" simply to cause discomfort (4). She, herself, is not immune to rash discrimination however, when she puzzles over one lady on board "with very pretty aristocratic features" but the "bronzed complexion of a gleaner" (4). The woman, a Miss Breakspear and her sister (see Fenton's portrait, same volume) are English orphans who Fenton later befriends, expressing guilty feelings about her initial rash judgments. Fenton's party (which includes her younger children 'Dall', 'May,' 'Deeny,' 'Fred,' and 'Hal') arrives at Boulogne, where they spend only one fortnight. Clara, who has spent three weeks already at Boulgone staying with John Emmett's family, joins them at an apartment above an Estaminet's (small café).
    Fenton's second daughter, Evelyn ('Dall') seems to have 'debuted' by 1862, as she and the eldest, Clara, are the subject of much of talk in Boulogne: "Care had been hoping Dall would make a sensation, and so she did. It was quite a study to observe mens faces shade over, seriously, as they stared at her, puzzled and awed by her purity" (26). Dall is characterized by both her grace and by her 'indifferent' look, which seems to put off some of her suitors. Count Voiscourt is particularly enchanted by Dall, and he asks her to dance several times at the balls. On an outing, Fenton meets a young Captain named De Savigny (see his portrait in this volume), an officer of the Tuileries artillery guard who waxes on about her daughters' innocence and perfection: "He assured me… that they were the most beautiful girls of the whole season, by far, and that every young man was raving"(58). Indeed, it seems everywhere they go, Fenton observes men in groups staring and talking about her daughters as "Quelles demoiselles" and Clara as "la princess Clotilde." Fenton is particularly taken by a "singularly handsome Englishman" she nicknames "Richard, Coeur de Lion," who appears to be interested in Clara (Fenton produces two watercolors of the gentleman). He shocks Fenton and her friend, Mrs. Hunter, who think him deceitful by masquerading with "very French manners, and that perfect accent" (45). A "handsome stern looking man" is also the subject of much scrutiny, and Fenton depicts him in several sketches. "Argus" as they nickname him, is "dreadfully strong in purposes" when asking Clara for dances. The lighthearted mischief-maker, Captain De Savigny, makes several overtures for Clara's hand in marriage, but Fenton discourages him. Finally, he concludes that England and France "would never unite, and it was [England's] fault for we indulged 'orgueuill' as a virtue" (95).
    As the children grow older and more self-reliant, Fenton seems to rely less on her servants, who only peripherally figure in this volume's entries. Fenton takes her children to the Vallée du Nacre, traveling the whole distance by foot. They are joined by Fenton's niece, Fanny Emmett, and soon meet with Major and Mrs. Hunter, and Mrs. Russell and her children. They return to the same mill they visited in 1854 (see vol. 2, and like then, her children are accused by the miller of eating his apples. Fenton retorts in French that she "knew them in 54 as uneatable crabs, fit for his pigs" (22). 'May', who is now fourteen, figures more prominently in this volume, most distinctly for her over-active imagination and the anti-Catholic views she seems to have inherited from her mother. "She has a source of constant fright here, from having read of the massacre of St. Bartholomew, and the priests are her constant dread" (12). 'May' and 'Deeny' are characterized "as the soul of propriety" and seem increasingly scandalized by raucous parties of carousers or processions of nuns and priests.
    Fenton refers to a book of her own sketches, entitled Week at Boulogne, which draws favorable attention from her friends, especially the Hunters. The Hunters ask if "they might lend my 'weeks sketches' to Mrs. Crowe, the authoress, as she had seen some and been much delighted, so much so, as to refuse walking with a party of people to look at them. They asked me to call on her, but I do not feel inclined for a selfish engagement that the children would not share" (46). The admirer of Fenton's sketches is likely Catherine Crowe, the popular English novelist, playwright and mesmerist whose works at this time period revolved around supernatural subjects.
    At the thought of leaving Boulogne, Fenton again returns to her melancholy: "I could see the English coast, and being reminded our holiday is over here, I also remembered I should soon return to a full sense of all my woes, which I own I have made, alas! For myself… When I am here again, on these ramparts, if I come – how shall I then fell, upon this subject?" (87). She includes a rare self-portrait to illustrate this scene. It is unclear what predicament Fenton will face upon her return to England.
    Watercolors; Diaries; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Travel sketches -- France; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Crowe, Catherine, 1790-1876; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary Fragment, Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 4 pages; 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 10(a))
    A loose page from a diary, most likely from Volume 9 (1862) or later. A watercolor drawing of "our last ball" shows Dall dancing in the officer's quadrille.
    Diaries; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Watercolors; Travel sketches -- France; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary Fragment, Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 page; 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 10(b))
    Loose pages of a journal by Ellen Fenton. This diary describes life in Ealing, England, suggesting that Fenton kept diaries when in England, separate from her Boulogne travel diaries. This fragment also indicates that her son "Dick" (Adolphous) worked for his father at John Fenton & Co. wine merchants.
    Diaries; Middlesex (England); Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813
  - Marriage certificate (copy) of John Fenton and Ellen Emmett, 1839 May 2, 2012; 1 certified copy of an entry of marriage; 17 x 37 cm.
    Marriage solemnized in the Parish of Walcot, Somerset. Presided by J.L. Wolley and witnessed Willshire John Emmett and Emma Katherine Gordon.
    Marriage certificates; Fenton, John, b. circa 1812; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813